<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://phoqus.us/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://phoqus.us/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-04-19T03:36:57+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Photonic Quantum Systems Group (PhoQuS)</title><subtitle>Learn more about the PhoQuS group and our research in quantum information science and quantum optics</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Saikat Guha Elevated to IEEE Fellow</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2025/01/25/Prof-Guha-IEEE-Fellow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Saikat Guha Elevated to IEEE Fellow" /><published>2025-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-19T03:34:09+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2025/01/25/Prof-Guha-IEEE-Fellow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2025/01/25/Prof-Guha-IEEE-Fellow.html"><![CDATA[<p>Clark Distinguished Chair Professor Saikat Guha has been named to the IEEE Fellow Class of 2025 for bridging information theory and physics to design quantum-enhanced photonic sensing, communications, and networking systems. Guha is appointed to the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) and leads the University of Maryland Photonic Quantum Systems Group (PhoQuS).</p>

<p><a href="https://clarknet.eng.umd.edu/news/news_story.php?id=16395">Link to ClarkNet Post here</a></p>

<hr />

<p>Clark Distinguished Chair Professor Saikat Guha has been named to the IEEE Fellow Class of 2025 for bridging information theory and physics to design quantum-enhanced photonic sensing, communications, and networking systems. Guha is appointed to the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) and leads the University of Maryland Photonic Quantum Systems Group (PhoQuS).</p>

<p>Guha joined ECE in June 2024 from the University of Arizona, College of Optical Sciences. His expertise in the growing field of quantum information research has further expanded ECE’s focus in quantum engineering.</p>

<p>His research interests include quantum information and estimation theory, quantum communications, and photonic quantum computing, and focuses on fundamental performance limits when light is used to extract, carry and process information.</p>

<p>PhoQuS is a joint venture between the University of Maryland and the University of Arizona. The group’s research is based on three main areas: mathematical foundations of quantum information theory, quantum optics, and photonic information processing. Their multi-disciplinary work connects areas such as information theory, quantum optics, physics of atomic systems, error correction theory, and network theory.</p>

<p>Since joining ECE, Guha has brought a breadth of funded research projects in conjunction with a number of organizations, including the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA), the Air Force Office of Scientific Research (AFOSR), the National Science Foundation (NSF), RTX, and Oak Ridge National Laboratories (ORNL) with the US Department of Energy (DoE),</p>

<p>After receiving a degree in Electrical Engineering from the Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur in 2002, he earned a SM (2004) and PhD (2008) in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science from MIT. Prior to joining the University of Arizona in 2017, he was with BBN Technologies in Cambridge, MA from 2008-2017, where he was part of the founding team of BBN’s Quantum Information Processing Group.</p>

<p>As a highly recognized quantum scientist, Guha has been the recipient of numerous awards, including the Raytheon 2011 Excellence in Engineering and Technology Award, the 2023 Anita Jones Entrepreneurial Award from BBN Technologies, and the Raymie Stata Award for outstanding performance as a Teaching Assistant for Signals and Systems at MIT. He was a member of India’s first team to the International Physics Olympiad in Reykjavik in 1998, where he received an Honorable Mention and the European Physical Society (EPS) Award for the experimental component.</p>

<h3 id="about-ieee-fellows">About IEEE Fellows</h3>

<p>The grade of Fellow recognizes unusual distinction in the profession and is reserved for a person with an outstanding record of accomplishments in any of the IEEE fields of interest. The accomplishments that are being honored have contributed importantly to the advancement or application of engineering, science and technology, bringing the realization of significant value to society at large.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Clark Distinguished Chair Professor Saikat Guha has been named to the IEEE Fellow Class of 2025 for bridging information theory and physics to design quantum-enhanced photonic sensing, communications, and networking systems. Guha is appointed to the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) and leads the University of Maryland Photonic Quantum Systems Group (PhoQuS).]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/saikat.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/saikat.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">CQN Winter School</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2024/11/21/CQN-Winter-School.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CQN Winter School" /><published>2024-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-19T03:34:09+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2024/11/21/CQN-Winter-School</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2024/11/21/CQN-Winter-School.html"><![CDATA[<p>The Center For Quantum Networks has announced the 2025 Winter School covering essential topics in the field of quantum information, optics, and networking. Learn more and <a href="https://cqn-erc.arizona.edu/2025winter-school">register here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Center For Quantum Networks has announced the 2025 Winter School covering essential topics in the field of quantum information, optics, and networking. Learn more and register here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/cqn.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/cqn.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Course Offering - Information in a Photon</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2024/11/21/Info-In-Photon.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Course Offering - Information in a Photon" /><published>2024-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-19T03:34:09+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2024/11/21/Info-In-Photon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2024/11/21/Info-In-Photon.html"><![CDATA[<p>Professor Saikat Guha will be teaching a new course at UMD for the Spring 2025 semester. This course will be open to both graduate and undergraduate students, and will be ideal for ECE students who would like to get a feel for why quantum treatment of light in the contexts of information processing (digital communications, sensing, imaging, etc.) offers fundamentally more powerful insights, and the design of systems with better performance than what is possible otherwise. No prior background in quantum mechanics, optics or information theory is necessary, but students who have a strong background in probability and linear algebra will find it the easiest to navigate the material.</p>

<h1 id="enee-439g739g-information-in-a-photon">ENEE 439G/739G: Information in a Photon</h1>
<h2 id="ece-special-topics-course">ECE Special Topics Course</h2>

<hr />

<h2 id="syllabus-pre-requisites-and-course-objectives">Syllabus, Pre-requisites, and Course Objectives</h2>

<h3 id="overview">Overview</h3>
<p>The goal of this course is to develop a rigorous understanding of the fundamental limits of the efficiency with which one can encode information in, and extract information from light, broadly in the contexts of communications and sensing.</p>

<p>To develop this understanding, the course covers:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Information Theory</strong>: Basics of the concept of information theory.</li>
  <li><strong>Estimation and Detection Theory</strong>: Essential aspects of these theories.</li>
  <li><strong>Optical Modes and Interference</strong>: Mathematical descriptions of orthogonal optical modes and interference.</li>
  <li><strong>Noise in Photodetection</strong>: Analysis as per the semiclassical theory of photodetection.</li>
</ul>

<p>The course explores examples from communications and sensing, demonstrating how:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Optical domain pre-processing of information-bearing light, and</li>
  <li>Novel receiver designs<br />
…can enhance information encoding and extraction compared to conventional means.</li>
</ol>

<p>It introduces the concept of “quantum limits” of information processing, exploring the best possible efficiency for encoding information in light as permitted by physical laws.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="course-objectives">Course Objectives</h3>
<p>Students will develop an appreciation for the advantages of treating light as a quantum mechanical object to glean richer information compared to classical electromagnetic wave treatments.</p>

<h4 id="primary-goals">Primary Goals:</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Equip students with deep intuitions on optical detection, laying the groundwork for research in quantum-enhanced photonic information processing.</li>
  <li>Develop an understanding of:
    <ol>
      <li>The value of quantum treatments of light to find the fundamental limits of encoding information.</li>
      <li>How pre-detection manipulation of light can optimize information extraction.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>This course assumes no background in optics, stochastic processes, quantum mechanics, information theory, or estimation theory. However, students should have proficiency in:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Complex numbers</li>
  <li>Probability theory</li>
  <li>Linear algebra (vectors and matrices)</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="pre-requisites">Pre-requisites</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Basic Fundamentals</strong>: ENEE101</li>
  <li><strong>Probability Theory</strong>: ENEE324 (or equivalent)</li>
  <li><strong>Linear Algebra</strong>: ENEE290 or MATH461 (advanced option)</li>
</ul>

<p>A background in quantum mechanics is not required but can be helpful.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="assignments">Assignments</h2>

<h3 id="homeworks">Homeworks</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Weekly problem sets, due the following week in class.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="advanced-problems">Advanced Problems</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Graduate Students</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>Solve one of ~20 Advanced Problems during the semester.</li>
      <li>Present the solution at an end-of-semester workshop.</li>
      <li>Advanced Problems include open-ended components that may lead to publishable research.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Undergraduate Students</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>Advanced Problems are fully optional.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="grades">Grades</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Undergraduate Students</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>Midterm Exams: <strong>50%</strong></li>
      <li>Homework: <strong>50%</strong></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Graduate Students</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>Midterm Exams: <strong>40%</strong></li>
      <li>Homework: <strong>30%</strong></li>
      <li>Advanced Problem: <strong>30%</strong></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Grades will be assigned on separate curves for undergraduate and graduate students.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="detailed-course-description">Detailed Course Description</h2>

<h3 id="modules-overview">Modules Overview</h3>
<p>The course is divided into three modules, each approximately 10 lectures.</p>

<h4 id="module-1-pre-detection-transformations-of-information-bearing-light">Module 1: Pre-Detection Transformations of Information-Bearing Light</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Quasimonochromatic laser light pulse and photon detection statistics.</li>
  <li>Linear interferometric transformations and optical-domain manipulations.</li>
  <li>Use of electro-optic feedback during detection.</li>
  <li>Binary state discrimination and quantum-optimal receiver designs.</li>
  <li>Introduction to quantum states of an optical mode (coherent states and number states).</li>
  <li>Open problems in quantum state discrimination.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="module-2-joint-detection-receiver-for-optical-communications">Module 2: Joint Detection Receiver for Optical Communications</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Brief introduction to classical information theory and Shannon capacity.</li>
  <li>Novel optical detection methods for laser-light modulated communications.</li>
  <li>Joint detection receivers and superadditivity in communications capacity.</li>
  <li>Modulation formats, error correction codes, and decoding algorithms.</li>
  <li>Derivation of the “quantum limit” of communications capacity.</li>
  <li>Open problems in error correction codes and receiver designs.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="module-3-novel-receivers-for-optical-sensing-and-imaging">Module 3: Novel Receivers for Optical Sensing and Imaging</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Introduction to detection theory, Fisherian, and Bayesian estimation theories.</li>
  <li>Applications to optical phase estimation and quantum-enhanced sensing.</li>
  <li>Standard quantum limit vs. Heisenberg limit for phase estimation.</li>
  <li>Applications in photonic sensors (gyroscopes, RF sensors, beam deflection).</li>
  <li>Fundamental “quantum limits” of sensing.</li>
  <li>Passive imaging and novel telescope receiver designs for higher resolution.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>The course concludes with a discussion of research avenues in:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Quantum optics</li>
  <li>Quantum information theory</li>
  <li>Photonic quantum information processing</li>
</ul>

<p>Advanced mathematical principles needed for future graduate-level courses will also be outlined.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Professor Saikat Guha will be teaching a new course at UMD for the Spring 2025 semester. This course will be open to both graduate and undergraduate students, and will be ideal for ECE students who would like to get a feel for why quantum treatment of light in the contexts of information processing (digital communications, sensing, imaging, etc.) offers fundamentally more powerful insights, and the design of systems with better performance than what is possible otherwise. No prior background in quantum mechanics, optics or information theory is necessary, but students who have a strong background in probability and linear algebra will find it the easiest to navigate the material.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/gmcap.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/gmcap.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Special Seminar - Isaac Harris</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2024/10/31/Special-Seminar-CQN.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Special Seminar - Isaac Harris" /><published>2024-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-19T03:34:09+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2024/10/31/Special-Seminar-CQN</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2024/10/31/Special-Seminar-CQN.html"><![CDATA[<p>The PhoQuS group is hosting a CQN-QUICS-JQI Special Seminar by Isaac Harris on November 19 from 2-3PM in the Atlantic Building ATL 3100A. It will also be accessible from Zoom meeting 942 6788 6806, passcode “quantum”.</p>

<p>Abstract: A spin-photon interface coupled to a local memory is a key component in brokered entanglement protocols for quantum communication and information processing. Group-IV color centers in diamond (SIV, GeV, and SnV) are promising candidates for this application, comprising an electronic spin with optical transitions acting as a spin-photon interface. However, the use of the intrinsic group-IV nuclear spin as a local memory for brokered entanglement remains an outstanding challenge, particularly for the heavier dopants, GeV and SnV, whose hyperfine features have not been extensively studied. Here, we present first-principles and experimental results characterising the hyperfine properties of the group-IV color centers. We discuss the effect of bias on the hyperfine levels, demonstrating a regime where the intrinsic nuclear spin can be used for brokered entanglement, and deriving expected coherence properties in this regime. We further demonstrate ground state spin control of a SnV-117 color center integrated in a photonic integrated circuit, showing 97.8% gate fidelity and 2.5 ms coherence time for the nuclear spin level. This lays the groundwork for brokered entanglement protocols with this system.</p>

<p>Bio: Isaac is a Ph.D. student in Electrical Engineering at MIT advised by Prof. Dirk Englund in the Quantum Photonics &amp; Al Group. His research interests are in the prediction, characterisation and large-scale integration of solid-state defects in semiconductors for use in emerging technologies such as quantum computing and quantum communication.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The PhoQuS group is hosting a CQN-QUICS-JQI Special Seminar by Isaac Harris on November 19 from 2-3PM in the Atlantic Building ATL 3100A. It will also be accessible from Zoom meeting 942 6788 6806, passcode “quantum”.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/isaac-harris-seminar.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/isaac-harris-seminar.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">PhoQuS Group &amp;amp; CQN at Quantum World Congress 2024</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2024/09/09/Quantum-World-Congress.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PhoQuS Group &amp;amp; CQN at Quantum World Congress 2024" /><published>2024-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-19T03:34:09+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2024/09/09/Quantum-World-Congress</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2024/09/09/Quantum-World-Congress.html"><![CDATA[<p>The PhoQuS group will be represented by members at the <a href="https://qsf.umd.edu">UMD Quantum Startup Foundry</a> booth at the Quantum World Congress from 9/9-9/11. Saikat Guha will also present on 9/10 in the session Architecting the Quantum Internet.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The PhoQuS group will be represented by members at the UMD Quantum Startup Foundry booth at the Quantum World Congress from 9/9-9/11. Saikat Guha will also present on 9/10 in the session Architecting the Quantum Internet.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/qsc.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/qsc.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Group Website</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2024/09/06/new-website.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Group Website" /><published>2024-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-19T03:34:09+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2024/09/06/new-website</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2024/09/06/new-website.html"><![CDATA[<p>The PhoQuS group is happy to announce our first semester as a team at the University of Maryland as a part of the Clark School of Engineering. We are launching this new group website to share information with the UMD community in beyond; covering our group research, projects, and general updates. Stay tuned over the coming months for more news about new funded projects and events.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The PhoQuS group is happy to announce our first semester as a team at the University of Maryland as a part of the Clark School of Engineering. We are launching this new group website to share information with the UMD community in beyond; covering our group research, projects, and general updates. Stay tuned over the coming months for more news about new funded projects and events.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/icon.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/icon.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>