<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://phoqus.us/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://phoqus.us/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-10-07T14:19:47+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Photonic Quantum Systems Group (PhoQuS)</title><subtitle>Learn more about the PhoQuS group and our research in quantum information science and quantum optics</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Presenting at Space Technology Showcase</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2025/10/07/ASTRA-Space-Technology-Showcase.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Presenting at Space Technology Showcase" /><published>2025-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T14:16:53+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2025/10/07/ASTRA-Space-Technology-Showcase</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2025/10/07/ASTRA-Space-Technology-Showcase.html"><![CDATA[<p>PhD student Jack Postlewaite will present an update on work related to the Green Machine receiver at the UMD Space Technology Showcase</p>

<hr />

<p>In the photon-starved depths of space, where data demands outstrip traditional RF links, a breakthrough emerges from the University of Maryland: a hardware-efficient super-additive joint detection optical receiver. Dubbed the Green Machine, this innovation pairs BPSK Hadamard modulation with a reconfigurable optical joint-detection receiver (O-JDR) to shatter classical limits. Achieving 3.15 bits per photon—surpassing the 2.88-bit plateau of symbol-by-symbol detection—it enables higher bandwidth, lower SWaP, and unregulated spectrum for Lunar and Martian missions. Led by Jack Postlewaite, Chaohan Cui, and collaborators from UMD, NASA Goddard, and UT Austin, the work demonstrates super-additivity via structured unitary transformations, paving the way for entanglement-free nonlocality in optical links.</p>

<p>The experiment unfolds on a fiber-optic platform: a 1550nm CW laser undergoes BPSK modulation into Hadamard codewords, attenuated to mimic deep-space loss, then processed through multi-stage interferometers with switchable delays and SNSPDs. Transition probability matrices from time-tagged photons reveal the receiver’s edge—GM4 outperforms PPM direct detection even under realistic losses. Reconfigurability via Sine-Cosine Fractal decomposition allows scalable unitaries without fixed stages, trading minor latency for adaptability. Results plot PIE against mean photon number, closing the gap to Holevo capacity and highlighting potential for quantum-enhanced variants.</p>

<p>This poster debuts at the inaugural UMD ASTRA Space Technology Showcase on October 15, 2025, from 1-3 PM in A. James Clark Hall’s Forum 1101. Hosted by UMD’s Center for Advanced Space Science and Technology Research, the event spotlights cross-campus innovations—from orbital debris detection to lunar rovers—fostering academia-industry-government ties. Keynote by Dr. Nancy Chabot of JHU APL details the DART mission’s asteroid deflection triumph, inspiring planetary defense parallels to optical comms resilience. Free with refreshments; register via astra.umd.edu to witness Maryland’s space tech vanguard.</p>

<p><a href="https://astra.umd.edu/events/space-technology-showcase">Learn more from the ASTRA event website</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[PhD student Jack Postlewaite will present an update on work related to the Green Machine receiver at the UMD Space Technology Showcase]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/AJC.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/AJC.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Postdoc Yu Shi Featured in PRX Quantum</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2025/06/02/Shi-featured-PRX.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Postdoc Yu Shi Featured in PRX Quantum" /><published>2025-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T14:16:53+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2025/06/02/Shi-featured-PRX</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2025/06/02/Shi-featured-PRX.html"><![CDATA[<p>Excited to share that one of our very own postdocs, Yu Shi, has been featured in a University of Maryland - A. James Clark School of Engineering news article!</p>

<p><a href="https://lnkd.in/eECmh6Tx">Link to the article here</a></p>

<hr />

<p>University of Maryland postdoc Yu Shi (ECE Ph.D. ’23) has been published as first author in PRX Quantum, a physical review journal produced by the American Physical Society (APS). His research was completed in collaboration with Dr. Ashlesha Patil, a scientist at PsiQuantum under the guidance of UMD Clark Distinguished Chair Professor Saikat Guha.</p>

<p>The basis of the paper, titled Stabilizer Entanglement Distillation and Efficient Fault-Tolerant Encoders, provides a framework for code-based distillation of quantum entanglement.</p>

<p>Quantum entanglement is essential in quantum information processing, but it is a noise-sensitive resource. Through his research, Shi presented a method for applying classical error-correcting codes to quantum entanglement distillation. Additionally, Shi has developed a measurement-based method that reduces circuity depth for entanglement distillation protocols based on stabilizer codes. Building this framework is a vital component for efficient quantum communication and fault-tolerant computing.</p>

<p>A key innovation noted in the paper is a constant-depth decoder, which uses single-qubit measurements to transform logical qubits into physical ones. This results in streamlined entanglement distillation for advanced codes such as quantum convolutional and quantum low-density parity-check (QLDPC) codes.</p>

<h3 id="about-prx-quantum">About PRX Quantum</h3>
<p>PRX Quantum is a highly selective journal in quantum information science and technology. It publishes works in multidisciplinary fields that showcases techniques, experiments, theory and understanding within the quantum community while supporting and encouraging the development of quantum research.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Excited to share that one of our very own postdocs, Yu Shi, has been featured in a University of Maryland - A. James Clark School of Engineering news article!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/yu.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/yu.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">PhoQuS Group Presentations at CLEO 2025</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2025/05/02/CLEO-Presentations.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PhoQuS Group Presentations at CLEO 2025" /><published>2025-05-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T14:16:53+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2025/05/02/CLEO-Presentations</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2025/05/02/CLEO-Presentations.html"><![CDATA[<p>The PhoQuS group will have members presenting at the CLEO 2025 conference. Check out presentations from Dr. Chaohan Cui in FS 2: Quantum Information and Communication on Tuesday, May 6th and FF115: Quantum networks - 2, May 9th. In a special symposium to celebrate the International Year of Quantum, Prof. Saikat Guha will be presenting in Symposium SY116 on Wednesday, May 7th. Finally, Jack Postlewaite will be presenting in session FF 119: Quantum Measurement and Metrology on Thursday, May 8th.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The PhoQuS group will have members presenting at the CLEO 2025 conference. Check out presentations from Dr. Chaohan Cui in FS 2: Quantum Information and Communication on Tuesday, May 6th and FF115: Quantum networks - 2, May 9th. In a special symposium to celebrate the International Year of Quantum, Prof. Saikat Guha will be presenting in Symposium SY116 on Wednesday, May 7th. Finally, Jack Postlewaite will be presenting in session FF 119: Quantum Measurement and Metrology on Thursday, May 8th.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/cleo-logo.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/cleo-logo.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Latest Issue of UMD’s EnTERPrise Magazine</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2025/04/30/Enterprise-Magazine.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Latest Issue of UMD’s EnTERPrise Magazine" /><published>2025-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T14:16:53+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2025/04/30/Enterprise-Magazine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2025/04/30/Enterprise-Magazine.html"><![CDATA[<p>Check out this latest issue of University of Maryland’s EnTERPrise Magazine: Building the Capital of Quantum! You may find some familiar faces (Saikat Guha and Jack Postlewaite) on page 23…</p>

<p><a href="https://lnkd.in/efUTgT3A">Check out the magazine here</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Check out this latest issue of University of Maryland’s EnTERPrise Magazine: Building the Capital of Quantum! You may find some familiar faces (Saikat Guha and Jack Postlewaite) on page 23…]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/enterprise.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/enterprise.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Recently Published in Nature - Superadditive communication with the green machine as a practical demonstration of nonlocality without entanglement</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2025/04/30/Nature-GreenMachine.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recently Published in Nature - Superadditive communication with the green machine as a practical demonstration of nonlocality without entanglement" /><published>2025-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T14:16:53+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2025/04/30/Nature-GreenMachine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2025/04/30/Nature-GreenMachine.html"><![CDATA[<p>Exciting research from our group—led by Dr. Chaohan Cui and PhD student Jack Postlewaite—was just recently published in the Nature Communications Journal! Their work presents the first experimental evidence of receiver-side superadditive communication capacity through joint detection. The realized receiver design offers a novel and scalable approach to implementing a Green Machine-type receiver. This design is also inherently resilient to channel phase noise without requiring a local oscillator. Together, these properties of superadditivity and phase noise resilience make it a strong contender for the design of near-term deep-space optical communication platforms.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-025-59107-4?utm_source=rct_congratemailt&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=oa_20250422&amp;utm_content=10.1038/s41467-025-59107-4">Read more about it here:</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="papers" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exciting research from our group—led by Dr. Chaohan Cui and PhD student Jack Postlewaite—was just recently published in the Nature Communications Journal! Their work presents the first experimental evidence of receiver-side superadditive communication capacity through joint detection. The realized receiver design offers a novel and scalable approach to implementing a Green Machine-type receiver. This design is also inherently resilient to channel phase noise without requiring a local oscillator. Together, these properties of superadditivity and phase noise resilience make it a strong contender for the design of near-term deep-space optical communication platforms.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/naturegreenmachine.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/naturegreenmachine.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Four students receiving their PhDs at the UArizona 2025 Commencement</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2025/04/21/2025-Grads.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Four students receiving their PhDs at the UArizona 2025 Commencement" /><published>2025-04-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T14:16:53+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2025/04/21/2025-Grads</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2025/04/21/2025-Grads.html"><![CDATA[<p>Four of our group’s students: Wenhua He, Prajit Dhara, Ian Tillman, and Ashlesha Patil will be walking across the stage at the University of Arizona on May 15. These four students have done remarkable work in their field and will be awarded their PhD’s this 2025 commencement.</p>

<p>Wenhua He defended her thesis on “Harnessing the Spatial Degree of Freedom for Quantum Photonic Sensors.” Ashlesha Patil defended her thesis on “Quantum Network Protocols and Architectures” and is now with PsiQuantum. Ian Tillman defended his thesis on “Continuous Variable Quantum Networks: A Layer Based Approach.” And just earlier this month, Prajit Dhara defended his thesis on “Quantum Communications with Near Term Quantum Networks.”</p>

<p>Join us on May 15 as we celebrate these four bright individuals!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Four of our group’s students: Wenhua He, Prajit Dhara, Ian Tillman, and Ashlesha Patil will be walking across the stage at the University of Arizona on May 15. These four students have done remarkable work in their field and will be awarded their PhD’s this 2025 commencement.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Saikat Guha Elevated to IEEE Fellow</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2025/01/25/Prof-Guha-IEEE-Fellow.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Saikat Guha Elevated to IEEE Fellow" /><published>2025-01-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T14:16:53+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2025/01/25/Prof-Guha-IEEE-Fellow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2025/01/25/Prof-Guha-IEEE-Fellow.html"><![CDATA[<p>Clark Distinguished Chair Professor Saikat Guha has been named to the IEEE Fellow Class of 2025 for bridging information theory and physics to design quantum-enhanced photonic sensing, communications, and networking systems. Guha is appointed to the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) and leads the University of Maryland Photonic Quantum Systems Group (PhoQuS).</p>

<p><a href="https://clarknet.eng.umd.edu/news/news_story.php?id=16395">Link to ClarkNet Post here</a></p>

<hr />

<p>Clark Distinguished Chair Professor Saikat Guha has been named to the IEEE Fellow Class of 2025 for bridging information theory and physics to design quantum-enhanced photonic sensing, communications, and networking systems. Guha is appointed to the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) and leads the University of Maryland Photonic Quantum Systems Group (PhoQuS).</p>

<p>Guha joined ECE in June 2024 from the University of Arizona, College of Optical Sciences. His expertise in the growing field of quantum information research has further expanded ECE’s focus in quantum engineering.</p>

<p>His research interests include quantum information and estimation theory, quantum communications, and photonic quantum computing, and focuses on fundamental performance limits when light is used to extract, carry and process information.</p>

<p>PhoQuS is a joint venture between the University of Maryland and the University of Arizona. The group’s research is based on three main areas: mathematical foundations of quantum information theory, quantum optics, and photonic information processing. Their multi-disciplinary work connects areas such as information theory, quantum optics, physics of atomic systems, error correction theory, and network theory.</p>

<p>Since joining ECE, Guha has brought a breadth of funded research projects in conjunction with a number of organizations, including the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (DARPA), the Air Force Office of Scientific Research (AFOSR), the National Science Foundation (NSF), RTX, and Oak Ridge National Laboratories (ORNL) with the US Department of Energy (DoE),</p>

<p>After receiving a degree in Electrical Engineering from the Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur in 2002, he earned a SM (2004) and PhD (2008) in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science from MIT. Prior to joining the University of Arizona in 2017, he was with BBN Technologies in Cambridge, MA from 2008-2017, where he was part of the founding team of BBN’s Quantum Information Processing Group.</p>

<p>As a highly recognized quantum scientist, Guha has been the recipient of numerous awards, including the Raytheon 2011 Excellence in Engineering and Technology Award, the 2023 Anita Jones Entrepreneurial Award from BBN Technologies, and the Raymie Stata Award for outstanding performance as a Teaching Assistant for Signals and Systems at MIT. He was a member of India’s first team to the International Physics Olympiad in Reykjavik in 1998, where he received an Honorable Mention and the European Physical Society (EPS) Award for the experimental component.</p>

<h3 id="about-ieee-fellows">About IEEE Fellows</h3>

<p>The grade of Fellow recognizes unusual distinction in the profession and is reserved for a person with an outstanding record of accomplishments in any of the IEEE fields of interest. The accomplishments that are being honored have contributed importantly to the advancement or application of engineering, science and technology, bringing the realization of significant value to society at large.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Clark Distinguished Chair Professor Saikat Guha has been named to the IEEE Fellow Class of 2025 for bridging information theory and physics to design quantum-enhanced photonic sensing, communications, and networking systems. Guha is appointed to the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE) and leads the University of Maryland Photonic Quantum Systems Group (PhoQuS).]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/saikat.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/saikat.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">CQN Winter School</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2024/11/21/CQN-Winter-School.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CQN Winter School" /><published>2024-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T14:16:53+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2024/11/21/CQN-Winter-School</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2024/11/21/CQN-Winter-School.html"><![CDATA[<p>The Center For Quantum Networks has announced the 2025 Winter School covering essential topics in the field of quantum information, optics, and networking. Learn more and <a href="https://cqn-erc.arizona.edu/2025winter-school">register here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Center For Quantum Networks has announced the 2025 Winter School covering essential topics in the field of quantum information, optics, and networking. Learn more and register here.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/cqn.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/cqn.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Course Offering - Information in a Photon</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2024/11/21/Info-In-Photon.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Course Offering - Information in a Photon" /><published>2024-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T14:16:53+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2024/11/21/Info-In-Photon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2024/11/21/Info-In-Photon.html"><![CDATA[<p>Professor Saikat Guha will be teaching a new course at UMD for the Spring 2025 semester. This course will be open to both graduate and undergraduate students, and will be ideal for ECE students who would like to get a feel for why quantum treatment of light in the contexts of information processing (digital communications, sensing, imaging, etc.) offers fundamentally more powerful insights, and the design of systems with better performance than what is possible otherwise. No prior background in quantum mechanics, optics or information theory is necessary, but students who have a strong background in probability and linear algebra will find it the easiest to navigate the material.</p>

<h1 id="enee-439g739g-information-in-a-photon">ENEE 439G/739G: Information in a Photon</h1>
<h2 id="ece-special-topics-course">ECE Special Topics Course</h2>

<hr />

<h2 id="syllabus-pre-requisites-and-course-objectives">Syllabus, Pre-requisites, and Course Objectives</h2>

<h3 id="overview">Overview</h3>
<p>The goal of this course is to develop a rigorous understanding of the fundamental limits of the efficiency with which one can encode information in, and extract information from light, broadly in the contexts of communications and sensing.</p>

<p>To develop this understanding, the course covers:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Information Theory</strong>: Basics of the concept of information theory.</li>
  <li><strong>Estimation and Detection Theory</strong>: Essential aspects of these theories.</li>
  <li><strong>Optical Modes and Interference</strong>: Mathematical descriptions of orthogonal optical modes and interference.</li>
  <li><strong>Noise in Photodetection</strong>: Analysis as per the semiclassical theory of photodetection.</li>
</ul>

<p>The course explores examples from communications and sensing, demonstrating how:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Optical domain pre-processing of information-bearing light, and</li>
  <li>Novel receiver designs<br />
…can enhance information encoding and extraction compared to conventional means.</li>
</ol>

<p>It introduces the concept of “quantum limits” of information processing, exploring the best possible efficiency for encoding information in light as permitted by physical laws.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="course-objectives">Course Objectives</h3>
<p>Students will develop an appreciation for the advantages of treating light as a quantum mechanical object to glean richer information compared to classical electromagnetic wave treatments.</p>

<h4 id="primary-goals">Primary Goals:</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Equip students with deep intuitions on optical detection, laying the groundwork for research in quantum-enhanced photonic information processing.</li>
  <li>Develop an understanding of:
    <ol>
      <li>The value of quantum treatments of light to find the fundamental limits of encoding information.</li>
      <li>How pre-detection manipulation of light can optimize information extraction.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>This course assumes no background in optics, stochastic processes, quantum mechanics, information theory, or estimation theory. However, students should have proficiency in:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Complex numbers</li>
  <li>Probability theory</li>
  <li>Linear algebra (vectors and matrices)</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="pre-requisites">Pre-requisites</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Basic Fundamentals</strong>: ENEE101</li>
  <li><strong>Probability Theory</strong>: ENEE324 (or equivalent)</li>
  <li><strong>Linear Algebra</strong>: ENEE290 or MATH461 (advanced option)</li>
</ul>

<p>A background in quantum mechanics is not required but can be helpful.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="assignments">Assignments</h2>

<h3 id="homeworks">Homeworks</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Weekly problem sets, due the following week in class.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="advanced-problems">Advanced Problems</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Graduate Students</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>Solve one of ~20 Advanced Problems during the semester.</li>
      <li>Present the solution at an end-of-semester workshop.</li>
      <li>Advanced Problems include open-ended components that may lead to publishable research.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Undergraduate Students</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>Advanced Problems are fully optional.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="grades">Grades</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Undergraduate Students</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>Midterm Exams: <strong>50%</strong></li>
      <li>Homework: <strong>50%</strong></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Graduate Students</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>Midterm Exams: <strong>40%</strong></li>
      <li>Homework: <strong>30%</strong></li>
      <li>Advanced Problem: <strong>30%</strong></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Grades will be assigned on separate curves for undergraduate and graduate students.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="detailed-course-description">Detailed Course Description</h2>

<h3 id="modules-overview">Modules Overview</h3>
<p>The course is divided into three modules, each approximately 10 lectures.</p>

<h4 id="module-1-pre-detection-transformations-of-information-bearing-light">Module 1: Pre-Detection Transformations of Information-Bearing Light</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Quasimonochromatic laser light pulse and photon detection statistics.</li>
  <li>Linear interferometric transformations and optical-domain manipulations.</li>
  <li>Use of electro-optic feedback during detection.</li>
  <li>Binary state discrimination and quantum-optimal receiver designs.</li>
  <li>Introduction to quantum states of an optical mode (coherent states and number states).</li>
  <li>Open problems in quantum state discrimination.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="module-2-joint-detection-receiver-for-optical-communications">Module 2: Joint Detection Receiver for Optical Communications</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Brief introduction to classical information theory and Shannon capacity.</li>
  <li>Novel optical detection methods for laser-light modulated communications.</li>
  <li>Joint detection receivers and superadditivity in communications capacity.</li>
  <li>Modulation formats, error correction codes, and decoding algorithms.</li>
  <li>Derivation of the “quantum limit” of communications capacity.</li>
  <li>Open problems in error correction codes and receiver designs.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="module-3-novel-receivers-for-optical-sensing-and-imaging">Module 3: Novel Receivers for Optical Sensing and Imaging</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Introduction to detection theory, Fisherian, and Bayesian estimation theories.</li>
  <li>Applications to optical phase estimation and quantum-enhanced sensing.</li>
  <li>Standard quantum limit vs. Heisenberg limit for phase estimation.</li>
  <li>Applications in photonic sensors (gyroscopes, RF sensors, beam deflection).</li>
  <li>Fundamental “quantum limits” of sensing.</li>
  <li>Passive imaging and novel telescope receiver designs for higher resolution.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>The course concludes with a discussion of research avenues in:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Quantum optics</li>
  <li>Quantum information theory</li>
  <li>Photonic quantum information processing</li>
</ul>

<p>Advanced mathematical principles needed for future graduate-level courses will also be outlined.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Professor Saikat Guha will be teaching a new course at UMD for the Spring 2025 semester. This course will be open to both graduate and undergraduate students, and will be ideal for ECE students who would like to get a feel for why quantum treatment of light in the contexts of information processing (digital communications, sensing, imaging, etc.) offers fundamentally more powerful insights, and the design of systems with better performance than what is possible otherwise. No prior background in quantum mechanics, optics or information theory is necessary, but students who have a strong background in probability and linear algebra will find it the easiest to navigate the material.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/gmcap.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/gmcap.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Special Seminar - Isaac Harris</title><link href="https://phoqus.us/2024/10/31/Special-Seminar-CQN.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Special Seminar - Isaac Harris" /><published>2024-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T14:16:53+00:00</updated><id>https://phoqus.us/2024/10/31/Special-Seminar-CQN</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://phoqus.us/2024/10/31/Special-Seminar-CQN.html"><![CDATA[<p>The PhoQuS group is hosting a CQN-QUICS-JQI Special Seminar by Isaac Harris on November 19 from 2-3PM in the Atlantic Building ATL 3100A. It will also be accessible from Zoom meeting 942 6788 6806, passcode “quantum”.</p>

<p>Abstract: A spin-photon interface coupled to a local memory is a key component in brokered entanglement protocols for quantum communication and information processing. Group-IV color centers in diamond (SIV, GeV, and SnV) are promising candidates for this application, comprising an electronic spin with optical transitions acting as a spin-photon interface. However, the use of the intrinsic group-IV nuclear spin as a local memory for brokered entanglement remains an outstanding challenge, particularly for the heavier dopants, GeV and SnV, whose hyperfine features have not been extensively studied. Here, we present first-principles and experimental results characterising the hyperfine properties of the group-IV color centers. We discuss the effect of bias on the hyperfine levels, demonstrating a regime where the intrinsic nuclear spin can be used for brokered entanglement, and deriving expected coherence properties in this regime. We further demonstrate ground state spin control of a SnV-117 color center integrated in a photonic integrated circuit, showing 97.8% gate fidelity and 2.5 ms coherence time for the nuclear spin level. This lays the groundwork for brokered entanglement protocols with this system.</p>

<p>Bio: Isaac is a Ph.D. student in Electrical Engineering at MIT advised by Prof. Dirk Englund in the Quantum Photonics &amp; Al Group. His research interests are in the prediction, characterisation and large-scale integration of solid-state defects in semiconductors for use in emerging technologies such as quantum computing and quantum communication.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The PhoQuS group is hosting a CQN-QUICS-JQI Special Seminar by Isaac Harris on November 19 from 2-3PM in the Atlantic Building ATL 3100A. It will also be accessible from Zoom meeting 942 6788 6806, passcode “quantum”.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://phoqus.us/images/isaac-harris-seminar.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://phoqus.us/images/isaac-harris-seminar.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>